Hello and welcome back to another video
with It's Dr. Dan and we're going to be
learning about what is a mole, which is
a concept that tends to be a little
overwhelming the first time we learn it.
But let's just try to explain exactly
what it is. So, is it this little fuzzy
little creature or is it something that
actually represents something in a
chemistry sense? So when it comes to
moles, the whole idea of it is that it's
an SI unit. So it's one of our basic
units just like uh meters or kilog. So
for this one, moles represents the
number of particles that we can find in
a given substance. And more
specifically, it's used for us as
scientists to be able to measure the
amount of a given substance. So what
what exactly does that mean? Well, it's
a way for us to be able to simplify
things. So if we take that mole, we're
trying to simplify our process. So one
way, how do we simplify things in our
everyday life? Well, one way is if I go
to the grocery store and you try to buy
a dozen eggs. Well, how many eggs are
you buying? Well, think about it that
way. So if I have one dozen, that's the
equivalent of saying that you have what?
12 eggs, right? Whenever we go through
any of these different processes. So if
we have 12 eggs, well that's something
that that came directly to your brain.
Well, a mole is something that's very
simple to or very similar to that
process. When we say that we have one
mole of a substance, well, we're going
to be first saying how many particles
there are. Well, for this one, the way
that we do that is that we say that we
have 6.022
* 10 23 particles. And now, why that
number? Well, that number in particular
is called Avagadro's
number. I like to think of it as it
means sounds like avocado, but it's
avagadro
number is how we represent that. So, one
mole is that many particles and that's a
really big number. But you got to
remember particles or atoms or ions or
any of these little species, they're so
tiny. They are something that we can't
physically see. So what can that be
represented with? Well, if I use, let's
say, the periodic table and we look up
carbon. Well, what mass does that
represent? Is that represented by? Well,
if you look on your periodic table,
you'll see that about 12.01
uh is the number that is being shown on
that periodic table, which is
represented in atomic mass units. Now
that atomic mass unit is something that
directly relates to the number of moles
and also it relates to something that we
can measure in the lab which is g. So
instead of using atomic mass units what
we're going to instead say is that all
right well if I measure out 12.01 g in
the lab on the balance what that
directly represents is 1 mole of carbon.
So that's a conversion term for
ourselves. So we can write that down,
right? 12.01 g of carbon all over one
mole of carbon or we can flip it
depending on what kind of dimensional
analysis type conversion we are doing.
However, how does that directly relate
to this term that we used above here and
um which was the term of the mole and
this Avagadro's number type effect here.
Well, being that if we have 12.01
g of carbon, that also as we mentioned
is 1 mole of carbon, but one mole of
carbon is 6.022
* 10 23 particles or in this case being
referring to the atom of carbon this is
atoms. All right? So, it's atoms of
carbon. So all those terms can be used
uh intricatally with one another using
our periodic table as conversion terms.
So this is a very powerful tool for us
in the near future. So if we look at
like any of these different elements on
the periodic table. So I have a bunch of
samples here that were measured in the
lab. So we just showed carbon for
example, right? If we measure about 12 g
out that represents one mole. Now if I
kind of look at some of these other
species like zinc or magnesium or copper
or sulfur silicon any of these and I
measure out the exact value that we see
on the periodic table that is measuring
out one mole. So let's take uh if we
take copper for example and we try to
find that on the periodic table. So when
we find that you see that all right well
it lists out that we have about 63.5
for6 g or amu what you're used to and
what we're going to do with that value
is that represents how many moles of
copper we have so why don't we write
that down so if we take that copper
value if I have 63.5 g of copper well
that's going to tell you that you have 1
mole of copper copper. It also tells you
that 1 mole of copper is equal to 6.022
* 10 23 atoms of copper. So we can use
those different methods as conversions.
So let's try to write that down. Let's
define all the different steps and
conversions we can use with the mole
that you're going to see in your
everyday chemistry class. So the first
one, what is it? So the first one is
molar mass. Molar mass is any time that
you're going between grams and moles. So
that is what you're going to be grabbing
from your periodic table.
Okay? So that is your periodic table
value
and that's what's going to show going
between those different values. So we're
going to be let's say if we pick
something um like sodium for example we
could define what its molar mass is. We
could see that all right well sodium if
we look at our periodic table has a very
very long uh molar mass but we can
define that really quickly as maybe just
say 22.99
g per mole. 22.99
g for every mole, right? And that is for
sodium. So we can define that. So what
other things can we come up with? Well,
there's also Avagadro's number. So that
would be the second one. So Avagadro's
number.
And how that is is for every any mole
that you have. So let's say if we
continue our example of sodium, well, we
could say that one mole of sodium is
equal to 6.022 022
* 10 23 atoms of sodium. Okay. Now, what
other things can we do? Well, there's
one other that we'll do in a little bit.
We can also define mole to mole
conversions. So, how could that work?
So, if I do a different color here. So,
mole to mole
conversions.
So what would be an example of that is
let's say if I take water and I ask you
all right if I have one mole of water
what else can that tell you well think
about your subscripts what do your
subscripts tell you well if I look at
this one we have two hydrogens
for every one oxygen that we have in
this formula right so two hydrogens for
every one oxygen So H2O. So what that
tells you is that for every one mole of
H2O, which is in this case a molecule,
we have two moles
of hydrogen.
We also have one mole of oxygen, which
are both elements. So this allows you to
be able to relate between compounds,
molecules, elements. So if you start
with a given mass for example, you can
maybe start seeing that there's going to
be conversions that are available to
you. So let's say if I pick a if I come
up with a problem where if I ask you
what is
the mass of a single
atom of carb of sodium?
How would we do that? Well, we could
kind of try to think, well, all right.
Well, if I have one atom
of sodium, well, how can I try to
convert atoms and try to cancel that
out? Well, we know that we have
Avagadra's number, which is referring to
atoms. So, if I kind of put this in my
little TA tables just to show these
little conversions. So, if we have 6.022
* 10 23 atoms
of sodium. Now, atoms cancels out atoms
and that's going to be equivalent to one
mole of sodium. Now, is that where we're
done? Well, we're trying to figure out
mass. So, what term can we go from mole
to mass? Well, that would be molar mass,
right? So, we can use the term that we
defined earlier. So we can say that one
mole
of sodium
is equivalent to that 22.99
g of sodium. So now we can show all
right well that's going to cancel out as
well where now moles of sodium cancels
moles of sodium and we definitely want
to write our units here. And now we're
just going to be left with only grams.
So we multiply everything on top. So be
1 mole * 1 mole * 22.99
divided by all the values that are on
the bottom. And what we are going to get
is 3.818
* 1023
g. So this shows you that all right well
if I go through all these little
calculations I can go from atoms to
moles to g. That's an extremely powerful
method for us to be able to use at our
disposal. Now what else can we do with
this? How can we try to figure out a
little bit of um all the different
pieces of the puzzle that we can show
here? Well, some other things we can do
is is we can also calculate mar mass of
compounds and molecules as well. So if I
take let's say water for example and I
ask you what is the molar mass of water?
Well, that's when we're going to be
using our periodic table from before.
So, we can see that. All right. Well, we
have hydrogen, which was about uh 1.008
grams. I'm moving things around is 1.008
g of
our different
molecule or atom here. And then we also
have oxygen. So, hydrogen is 1.08
g per mole. oxygen is 15.999
gram per mole. So we what we can do is
we can add up all these values and
multiply it by whatever its subscript
is. So if I have two hydrogens, right,
we're going to multiply hydrogen by two
and I have one oxygen. We're going to
take all those values and then add them
together. So if I go through that
process and I add up that I have 1.008
008 g per mole and then the roughly 16 g
per mole for oxygen. We're going to get
approximately 18.02
g per mole for H2O. And that's with a
little bit of rounding just to kind of
give me some uh slack here when it comes
to showing how to do that. But we're
just adding up the different values. So
this is a conversion term that we can
use in future problems. Let's try
another one. Let's say if I wanted to
add up the molar mass of let's say if I
give you uh maybe glucose. So if we have
glucose which is C6 H12 06. So this is a
pretty big molecule. We can go through
and try to do the same thing use our
subscripts. So if I start with carbon
right we have six carbons. We can use
our periodic table to look up the molar
mass which is about uh 12.009
amu.
We can then look up how many hydrogens
there are. So hydrogen there are 12 of
them. Sorry, we're using grams per mole
in this case.
Hydrogen there's 12 of them. So that's
going to be 1.00
uh 8 g per mole.
So, let's try to color code these for
ourselves. And 12 and 12. And then for
oxygen,
what we're going to do is that there's
six of them. So, this is going to be
times that 15.99
g per mole. So, you're going to take 6 *
12.9,
add it to the 12 * 1.8, 8 add it to the
6 * 15.999
and then we'll get our molar mass for a
bigger compound which is 180.142
amu. Okay, so it's given us that ability
to solve for all kinds of different
problems or uh in these different things
and I keep saying amu but we're doing
grams per mole cuz we're working on
molar mass, right? So this is for
glucose. So, if I asked you, let's say
if I had um maybe if we wanted to figure
out how many moles there are in this
particular compound, we could do that.
So, we have glucose. So, we could say
that we have one mole
of glucose.
How many moles of carbon are there? How
many moles of hydrogen are there? How
many moles of oxygen? Well, for every
one mole of glucose, we're going to have
one mole or sorry 6 moles of carbon,
12 moles of hydrogen and six moles of
oxygen. So with that, these are how you
can define your mole to mole ratios,
which is what I talked about step three
from earlier of how you can do some
major conversions. So, let's say if I
had um 10 g of glucose
and I wanted to know how many grams
of oxygen
are in 10 g
of glucose. How would we do that? Well,
this can be a little bit of a harder
problem. Why don't we try setting it up?
So if I have 10 g, the first thing is is
the goal is always the mole. Okay? So if
you can convert to moles, you can then
convert it to anywhere. So the goal is
the mole. So if I have 10 g of C6 H1206,
how would we get to moles? Well, that's
where our molar mass is going to come
in, which we calculated earlier. So it's
going to be that 180.142 g per mole.
Now, being that we want to cancel out
grams,
so that's going to go on the bottom
here. Those two units are going to
cancel and that's going to be equivalent
to every one mole of C6 H12 06. So, that
gets us to moles. We got our goal.
However, we want to get to oxygen. So,
what can I define next? Well, we can
look at our subscripts and define the
ratio of moles of oxygen to moles of
glucose. So, if we have one mole
of glucose,
that will cancel out these values here
and that's going to be equivalent to six
moles of oxygen.
So by doing that, that allows you to all
of a sudden go from having grams to
moles.
Now we cancelled that out and now we're
left with only moles of oxygen, which is
a very useful conversion. We just
converted something from one species to
another. This gives you predictability
in chemistry. So now our last step is
being that we want g of oxygen. What do
we need? Moles to golar mass. So 1 mole
of oxygen is going to be equivalent to
15.999
g of oxygen. And that gives you your
final conversion
and giving you g. So if we were to solve
all that, how would we do it? Well,
we're going to take 10 * 6. So 10 time
so 10 g * 6 moles times 15.999.
Then we're going to divide that by
180.142
* 1 * 1. And what we are going to get is
that in 10 g of glucose, we have
approximately 5 328
g of oxygen. Now, being that I only had
two sigfigs in my original problem,
we'll round it to two sigfigs. So that
would be 5.3 g of oxygen. And that's for
sigfigs.
And that would be how you can put all
these different conversions together. I
hope this video helped a little bit.
There'll be more to come. Please let me
like and subscribe and let me know what
other future videos you might need.
Thank you and I hope you all have a
wonderful day.
[Music]